<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The Probability and the Word</title>
    <link>https://carlosdanieljimenez.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on The Probability and the Word</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://carlosdanieljimenez.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>MLflow for Generative AI Systems</title>
      <link>https://carlosdanieljimenez.com/post/mlflow_genai/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://carlosdanieljimenez.com/post/mlflow_genai/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;mlflow-for-generative-ai-systems&#34;&gt;MLflow for Generative AI Systems&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll start this post by recalling what Hayen said in her book &lt;strong&gt;Designing Machine Learning Systems (2022): &amp;lsquo;Systems are meant to learn&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/strong&gt; This statement reflects a simple fact: today, LLMs and to a lesser extent vision language models are winning in the Data Science world. But how do we measure this learning? RLHF work is always a good indicator that perplexity will improve, but let&amp;rsquo;s return to a key point: LLMs must work as a system, therefore debugging is important, and that&amp;rsquo;s where the necessary tool for every Data Scientist, AI Engineer, ML Engineer, and MLOps Engineer comes in: MLflow.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Decline of a Framework</title>
      <link>https://carlosdanieljimenez.com/post/tensorflow/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://carlosdanieljimenez.com/post/tensorflow/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;reflections-on-tensorflow-in-the-context-of-the-modern-ai-engine-and-the-evolving-role-of-data-scientists&#34;&gt;Reflections on TensorFlow in the context of the modern AI engine and the evolving role of Data Scientists&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Throughout my journey in the world of data, I’ve witnessed many changes — some tools fading out of popularity while others take the spotlight. R, for example, has become more niche, used mostly by statisticians and academics. Flask, once a common choice for lightweight APIs, gradually gave way to FastAPI thanks to its modularity and support for asynchronous features, redefining how APIs are designed and deployed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Raspberry Pi 16GB, Servers, and MLOps</title>
      <link>https://carlosdanieljimenez.com/post/mlops-servers-raspberry/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://carlosdanieljimenez.com/post/mlops-servers-raspberry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Less than two months ago, the most powerful version of the Raspberry Pi 5 hit the market, featuring 16GB of RAM. While its price ($120 USD) is a valid discussion point, as someone who uses these devices as servers for deployment testing and efficiency evaluation at the code level, I want to explore its utility from a &lt;strong&gt;computer science perspective&lt;/strong&gt; in the context of &lt;strong&gt;MLOps and LLMs testing&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;raspberry-pi-utility&#34;&gt;Raspberry Pi Utility&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s start with some common applications to build on ideas:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MLops into Raspberry Pi 5</title>
      <link>https://carlosdanieljimenez.com/post/mlops_raspberrypi5/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://carlosdanieljimenez.com/post/mlops_raspberrypi5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the tools I use most for practicing &lt;strong&gt;MLOps&lt;/strong&gt;, both for designing pipelines and APIs (for inference), is the &lt;strong&gt;Raspberry Pi&lt;/strong&gt;. Today, I spent several hours trying to install &lt;strong&gt;Visual Studio Code&lt;/strong&gt; to complement my &lt;strong&gt;iPad Pro&lt;/strong&gt; as a development tool.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-this-setup-&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why this setup?&lt;/strong&gt; 🤔&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Improve programming skills—I am a big fan of using &lt;strong&gt;Weights &amp;amp; Biases (W&amp;amp;B)&lt;/strong&gt; to monitor the resource usage of each service I create.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Using the &lt;strong&gt;Raspberry Pi as a server&lt;/strong&gt; allows me to test &lt;strong&gt;Edge computing&lt;/strong&gt; deployments.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;For &lt;strong&gt;scalable prototype development&lt;/strong&gt;, it’s a great way to test artifacts and the &lt;strong&gt;lifecycle of models&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;When designing a model from &lt;strong&gt;hyperparameters&lt;/strong&gt;, it helps me fine-tune &lt;strong&gt;grid search&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;Bayesian methods&lt;/strong&gt; efficiently to optimize experimentation.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Running &lt;strong&gt;MLflow on Edge computing&lt;/strong&gt; enables &lt;strong&gt;optimization&lt;/strong&gt; in model registry and updates.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Using Docker and Kubernetes&lt;/strong&gt; helps ensure &lt;strong&gt;clean code&lt;/strong&gt; before committing changes.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are many more reasons, but these are the main ones. Now, how do you set up &lt;strong&gt;Raspberry Pi&lt;/strong&gt; to unlock its full power for MLOps?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://carlosdanieljimenez.com/post/artifacts-designs/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://carlosdanieljimenez.com/post/artifacts-designs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;artifact-design-and-pipeline-in-mlops-part-i&#34;&gt;Artifact Design and Pipeline in MLOps Part I&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In MLOps, most of the work focuses on the &lt;strong&gt;inference stage&lt;/strong&gt;, specifically the development of microservices. However, the broader picture goes beyond this—it includes aspects ranging from programming practices to resource utilization that need to be evaluated. This is where the role of a &lt;strong&gt;Machine Learning DevOps Engineer&lt;/strong&gt; becomes crucial. In this post, I want to address this profile by approaching it from the perspective of designing a model.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Edge Computing and Edge Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://carlosdanieljimenez.com/post/edge-computing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://carlosdanieljimenez.com/post/edge-computing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&#xA;  &lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/carlosjimenez88M/carlosjimenez88m.github.io/blob/master/images/WhatsApp%20Image%202024-10-14%20at%2016.46.42.jpeg?raw=true&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Data scientists often face three possibilities when deploying our products into production: through the cloud, edge computing, or the more recent variant, Edge Machine Learning. To introduce these concepts and provide context for this post, I will start by discussing the foundation—AI Computing.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;ai-computing-and-the-rigor-of-mathematics&#34;&gt;AI Computing and the Rigor of Mathematics&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A promise of computing is to make machines learn, and this is the job of the data scientist. When applying a model to data, Alan Turing&amp;rsquo;s insight from 1947 remains highly relevant. He simply stated that &amp;ldquo;machines learn from experience&amp;rdquo; (train set), a concept now popularized as data-driven methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Clean White Theme for Hugo</title>
      <link>https://carlosdanieljimenez.com/post/readme/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://carlosdanieljimenez.com/post/readme/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;clean-white-theme-for-hugo&#34;&gt;Clean White Theme for Hugo&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;CleanWhite is a clean, elegant, but fully functional blog theme for Hugo. Here is a live &lt;a href=&#34;https://zhaohuabing.com&#34;&gt;demo site&lt;/a&gt; using this theme.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is based on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Huxpro/huxpro.github.io&#34;&gt;huxblog Jekyll Theme&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/BlackrockDigital/startbootstrap-clean-blog-jekyll&#34;&gt;Clean Blog Jekyll Theme&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;These two upstream projects have done awesome jobs to create a blog theme, what I&amp;rsquo;m doing here is porting it to Hugo, of which I like the simplicity and the much faster compiling speed. Some other features which I think could be useful, such as site search with algolia and proxy for Disqus access in China, have also been built in the CleanWhite theme. Other fancy features of upstream projects are not supported by this Hugo theme, I&amp;rsquo;d like to make it as simple as possible and only focus on blog purpose, at least for now.&#xA;While I created this theme, I followed the Hugo theme best practice and tried to make every part of the template as a replaceable partial html, so it could be much easier for you to make your customization based on it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://carlosdanieljimenez.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://carlosdanieljimenez.com/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;about-me&#34;&gt;About Me&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m Colombian! and I live in a city surrounded by the sea and the mountains.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I have been working in the data industry for &lt;strong&gt;over a decade&lt;/strong&gt;, having served roles from &lt;strong&gt;Statistician&lt;/strong&gt; all the way to &lt;strong&gt;AI Engineer&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Recently, I have focused on working as an &lt;strong&gt;ML DevOps Engineer&lt;/strong&gt;, specializing in the &lt;strong&gt;Machine Learning Design System&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Agentic AI Engineering&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To stay sharp in &lt;strong&gt;AI Programming&lt;/strong&gt; and refine my scripting strategies, I work with a &lt;strong&gt;Raspberry Pi&lt;/strong&gt; connected to an &lt;strong&gt;iPad Pro&lt;/strong&gt;, and I debug and evaluate my code using &lt;strong&gt;Weights &amp;amp; Biases&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://carlosdanieljimenez.com/notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://carlosdanieljimenez.com/notes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;go-语言学习笔记&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://zhaohuabing.com/learning-golang&#34;&gt;Go 语言学习笔记&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;envoy-学习笔记&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://zhaohuabing.com/learning-envoy&#34;&gt;Envoy 学习笔记&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://carlosdanieljimenez.com/search/placeholder/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://carlosdanieljimenez.com/search/placeholder/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Posts Archive</title>
      <link>https://carlosdanieljimenez.com/archive/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://carlosdanieljimenez.com/archive/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
