<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Music-Analysis on The Probability Engine</title><link>https://carlosdanieljimenez.com/tags/music-analysis/</link><description>Recent content in Music-Analysis on The Probability Engine</description><generator>Hugo -- 0.147.3</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://carlosdanieljimenez.com/tags/music-analysis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Attention Windows: A Novel Framework for Measuring Narrative Cognitive Load in Beatles vs Pink Floyd</title><link>https://carlosdanieljimenez.com/post/2026-02-10-attention-windows-beatles-floyd/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://carlosdanieljimenez.com/post/2026-02-10-attention-windows-beatles-floyd/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This research introduces &lt;strong>Attention Windows&lt;/strong>, a novel framework for measuring the cognitive span required by listeners to follow lyrical narratives. How long can a theme persist before the lyrics shift to something new? Building on previous semantic embedding analyses of the Beatles and Pink Floyd, we develop a multi-method approach to quantify this narrative architecture across two iconic albums: &lt;em>The Dark Side of the Moon&lt;/em> and &lt;em>Abbey Road&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Core Finding (UNEXPECTED):&lt;/strong> The analysis reveals a systematic failure of distributional semantics to capture abstract thematic coherence in progressive rock. The Beatles exhibit significantly longer attention windows (μ = 0.57 lines, SD = 1.48) than Pink Floyd (μ = 0.25 lines, SD = 0.97) when measured with OpenAI&amp;rsquo;s text-embedding-ada-002 at its calibrated threshold (θ = 0.85). This counterintuitive result (p &amp;lt; 0.01, Cohen&amp;rsquo;s d = -0.24) exposes a fundamental limitation: transformer-based embeddings, trained on distributional statistics from web corpora, systematically privilege &lt;strong>type-level lexical overlap&lt;/strong> (repeated tokens, n-grams) over &lt;strong>token-level conceptual continuity&lt;/strong> (abstract themes expressed through synonymy, metaphor, and semantic field variation). The Beatles&amp;rsquo; verse-chorus architecture creates high embedding similarity through verbatim repetition, while Pink Floyd&amp;rsquo;s through-composed approach—deploying varied metaphorical expressions of unified philosophical themes—produces orthogonal embedding vectors despite conceptual unity. This is not a quirk of ada-002 but a structural property of distributional semantics: co-occurrence statistics cannot distinguish &amp;ldquo;same theme, different words&amp;rdquo; from &amp;ldquo;different themes, same words.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>